A Finding Aid to the Paul Ryan papers, 1931-2009, in the Archives of American Art AAA.ryanpaul
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1965-2007; Series 2; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  - Paul Ryan, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Paul Ryan, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Paul Ryan, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Paul Ryan, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Paul Ryan, 1995-2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Paul Ryan, circa 1965-2008 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - S, 1968-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
    Contains correspondence with Willioughby Sharp and Bob Schuler.
  - Savannah College of Art and Design, 1991-1995 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Trent Schroyer, 1980-1999 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Phyllis Gershuny Segury, 1974-2000 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Michael Shamberg, circa 1977-1995 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Jodie Sibert, circa 1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Charlene Spretnak, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Marita Sturken, 1983-1989 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - T, 1975-2004 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Contains correspondence form Parry Teasdale.
  - U, 1977-2005 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - United States Information Agency, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - V, circa 1969-1985 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Video Data Bank, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Visual Studies Workshop, 1984-1999 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - W, 1968-2001 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - W.W. Norton & Co., 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1988-1999 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Greg Williams, 1982-1989 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Bruce Wilshire, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Howard Wise, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - WNET/Thirteen, 1977-1996 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Y-Z, 1977-1993 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Contains correspondence from Jud Yalkut.
  - Gene Youngblood, circa 1969 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - First Name Only, A-C, 1974-2003 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - First Name Only, D-F, 1966-1995 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - First Name Only, G-H, 1968-1998 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - First Name Only, J-M, 1965-2005 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - First Name Only, N-Y, 1964-2004 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Unsigned or Illegible Signature, circa 1979-1996 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Oversized broadside from box 2, folder 49. (Box 20)
- Writings, 1955-2001; Series 3; 6.8 Linear feet Boxes 3-10, 20
  Writings are arranged by type of material. Most of the writings are arranged alphabetically by title if one exists, or by subject matter if no title is given. Notebooks were processed to a minimal level and arranged chronologically. Notebooks containing notes relating to a single project or work are filed with that project or work. Those filed in this series have heterogeneous content and cover a range of subjects. Note cards and loose notes were sorted loosely by subject during processing.
  Significant additional writings are also found in series 5, Project Files, in the form of project documentation and proposals. Writings in published form are found in series 7, Printed Material. A lengthy script and drafts of the project "Video Wake for my Father" by Ryan is found in Series 5.3 Other Projects. Writings and other records related to Earthscore are found in series 4, Organizational Records.
  Writings include mainly articles, lectures, book drafts, and notebooks by Ryan. Also found are poetry, short stories, a treatment for a television show, and writings by others in various genres. Most of Ryan's prose writing is theoretical in nature, although personal writings and notes from projects are also found. His core ideas are found in multiple forms, re-worked and revised for new publications and new applications. Articles include both published and unpublished writings, with some published multiple times under different titles. Some of the writings filed under articles are short essays in draft form which may have been incorporated into other works. Several of the articles were later collected in books. Books are documented with multiple drafts of Cybernetics of the Sacred and Video Mind, Earth Mind, as well as contracts and correspondence with publishers, layout documents, and notes. The article "Art and Survival: The Earthscore Notational System" brings together many of Ryan's core theories and ideas about their implementation.
  Notebooks include over 100 notebooks spanning 40 years, and are arranged chronologically. Many notebooks contain notes related to later published works or projects, and such notes can be located by the date of the work. Notebooks in this series typically cover many subjects or do not relate in an obvious way to a single project. Some of the early notebooks have a subject written by Ryan on their cover, and where this is the case it has been included in the container listing. Some of the early notebooks are more like journals, and others contain journal entries along with drafts of letters, articles, or project notes.
  - Articles (Box 3)
    - Art and Survival: The Earthscore Notational System for Sharing Perception of the Natural World, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      Oversized illustration housed in Box 20.
    - Attempting a Calculus of Intention, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Bateson, Brand, Brown: Ideas Becoming Ideology? Ecology Becoming Mythology?, circa 1977 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Gender and Threeing in Cyberspace, circa 2001 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - A Genealogy of Video, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - A General Method of Modeling, circa 1985 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Guerrilla Strategy and Cybernetic Theory, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Articles (Box 4)
    - Jesus Crucified, The Living Earth and Television, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Keynote Hits Sour Note, or Halleck Is Wrong about McLuhan, circa 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Living Between Ice and Fire by the River that Runs Both Ways, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - A Logic of Relationships, circa 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - A Metalogue: Gregory Bateson, Paul Ryan, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Notes Toward Expo '76, circa 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - On Personal Computers and Investing, circa 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Personal Essay on Leaving the Passionist Monastery, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
    - Positional Intelligence/Planetary Culture, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Probing War with McLuhan, circa 1968 (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
    - Raging Beauty: Gillette's Photoshop Prints, circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Relationships, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - A Ritual of Triadic Relationships Determined by the Topology of a Non-Orientable Circuit, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 15-19)
    - Roadside Dirt from the Reading Prong, circa 1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Sacred Chreods, circa 1974 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Threeing, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Toward an Information Economy, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Video, Computers, and Memory, circa 1989 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Videotape: The Medium is ???, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Water Wisdom, circa 1986 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - The Work of Art in the Age of Electronic Circuitry, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 27-33)
  - Books (Box 4)
    - Cybernetics of the Sacred, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 34-37)
    - Video Mind, Earth Mind, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 37-38)
  - Book Proposals (Box 5)
    - Brown and the Limits to Politics, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Electronic Media and the Ecological Crisis, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - From Red to Green: A Proposal for Perestroika from an American, circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Relationships, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Television and the Death of Nature, circa 1990 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Striped Bass Bioregion: Reinhabiting the Lower Hudson, circa 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - The Video Cookbook, circa 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Video Possibilities, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Video Realism and Reinhabitation, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Video Vision for Cyberspace, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Video and Memory, circa 1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Lectures (Box 5)
    - American Video Art and the Future of European Television, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Education for Sustainability, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Face to Face in a Wired World, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
    - Is the Computer Revolution Real?, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - McLuhan and Earthscore, circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Montage, Remote Sensing, and Ecological Television, circa 1993 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - A Non-Orientable Circuit, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - A Sign of Iteself, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Video as Evolutionary Tool: Triadic Relations, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 22-24)
    - Video as a Tool of Firstness, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Video Realism and Reinhabitation (Lecture Series), circa 1983 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Notebook, "The Philosophy of Paul Ryan", 1959 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Notebook, "Surrealist", 1966 June (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Notebook, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Notebook, "VT #1", 1968 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Notebook, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Notebook, circa 1968 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Notebook, 1969 September (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Notebook, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Notebook, circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Notebook, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Notebook, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Notebook, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Notebook, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Notebook, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Notebook, circa 1973 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Notebook, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Notebook, "California, Bateson", circa 1977 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Notebook, "Gillette", circa 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Notebooks, circa 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 44-48)
  - Notebooks, circa 1980 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Notebooks, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Notebook, "Poem, Cape Cod, Gloucester Station", 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Notebook, circa 1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Notebook, "Computer, Consensus, Poem", 1982 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Notebooks, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
  - Notebooks, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Notebooks, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 12-13)
  - Notebook, circa 1984 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, 1984-1985 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Notebook, circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Notebook, "Video, Remembrance", circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Notebook, circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Notebooks, circa 1985 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Notebooks, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 4-10)
  - Notebooks, circa 1986 (Box 7, Folder 11-15)
  - Notebook, 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Notebook, "Living Earth", 1987 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Notebooks, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 18-22)
  - Notebooks, circa 1987 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Notebook, 1987-1990 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Notebooks, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
  - Notebooks, circa 1988 (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
  - Notebooks, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - Notebook, "Travel Notes," Aachen, Germany, circa 1989 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Notebooks, circa 1989 (Box 8, Folder 13-16)
  - Notebooks, circa 1980-1989 (Box 8, Folder 17-23)
  - Notebooks, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
  - Notebook, circa 1990 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Notebooks, 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - Notebook, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Notebook, circa 1992 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Notebook, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Notebook, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Notebooks, circa 1996 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
  - Notebook, circa 1998 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Notebooks, circa 1999 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
  - Notebook, circa 2000 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Note Cards (Box 9)
    - Alcoholism, circa 1959 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Computer Uses, circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Labor and Jobs, circa 1993 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Philosophy and Religion, circa 1964 (Box 9, Folder 21-23)
    - Television and Videotape, circa 1970 (Box 9, Folder 24-25)
    - War and Future, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Notes (Box 9)
    - General, circa 1968-2000 (Box 9, Folder 27-32)
    - Bibliographic, circa 1970-1993 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Bioregional, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Oversized notes housed in Box 20.
    - Cybernetic City, circa 1973 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - The Earthscore Method of Video Production, circa 1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Moebius Strip, circa 1969 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Notes from a Trip to Turkey, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Oversized item housed in Box 20.
    - On Education and Sustainability, circa 1992 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - On Environment and Climate Change, circa 1998 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - On Threeing, circa 1990 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - "Taped to Wall", circa 1975 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Poetry, circa 1980-2000 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - "Poem Book", circa 1964 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Short Stories, circa 1955-1965 (Box 10, Folder 13-14)
  - Treatment, Robots and Kids, aka The Pursuit of Happiness, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Writings by Others (Box 10)
    - "Adam's Arcade" by Don Delo, circa 1983 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - The Coming Synthesis - Chronetics and Cybernation by Victor Gioscia, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Differentiated Syncretion: Jealousy, unattributed, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Gestalt Therapy: Dreaming for Rebels, unattributed, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Lost Ancestors: An Introduction to Pooch Van Dunk's 'Indian Heritage' by Peter Lamborn Wilson, circa 1993 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - McBot and Son, by Alan Kott, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Metarap: Who You Are is How You Change, by Victor Gioscia, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Papers Presented at the Charles S. Peirce Sesquicentennial International Congress, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 23-26)
    - Poetry by Jim Ryan and Others, circa 1965-2000 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - Practice Dying and Dance as Often as You Can, by Victor Gioscia, circa 1980 (Box 10, Folder 28)
    - The Six Permutations, by Myrdene Anderson, circa 1991 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    - The Subversion of Experience, by Davidson Gigliotti, circa 1995 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - Summary of Presentation by Betty Kronsky and Paul Ryan, "Triadic Relationships: the Hypnotic Power of Position" for NYSEPH, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - Untitled Manuscript by Jean Gardner, circa 2000 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - Video Art Now, by David Gigliotti and Ira Schneider, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    - Watch Out Dick Tracy, by Dee Dee Halleck, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified Fragments, circa 1990-2000 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Oversized illustration from the article housed in Box 3, folder 45 (Box 20)
  - Oversized notes from Box 10, folder 2 (Box 20)
  - Oversized notes from Box 10, folder 6 (Box 20)
- Organizational Records, 1968-1996; Series 4; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 10-11, 20, OV 21
  Organizational records include writings, correspondence, printed material, financial records, grant proposals, and other records concerning various organizations, collectives, and companies in which Ryan participated, mostly having to do with environmental advocacy, video production, or a combination of the two. Organizations with substantial records in this series include the Earth Environmental Group, the Earthscore Foundation, Environment '89 (and '90, '91, and '92), the Gaia Institute, Raindance Corporation, Responsive Environments Corporation, and Space Videoarts.
  Documentation of the organization the Earthscore Foundation includes financial records, by-laws, writings, grant proposals, and printed material. Writings outline Ryan's Earthscore Notational System, among other projects. Grant proposals also contain significant description of the organization's projects. Gaia Institute records include mainly writings and notes, including a proposal for a conference series, "Professionals for the Earth."
  Raindance Corporation records include a partial transcript of a 1970 interview with Ryan, excerpts of which appeared in the 2nd issue of Radical Software magazine, an essay about the video "Supermarket," flyers, lists of Raindance video productions, and exhibition announcements from a 1991 retrospective at the Whitney museum. A single contact sheet is unlabeled but contains photographs of Ryan, Buckminster Fuller, and possibly David Cort and Ira Schneider.
  Responsive Environments Corporation records contain notes and writings produced by Ryan on potential commercial and educational uses for video, written in 1968 and 1969. Space Videoarts records include correspondence, financial records, grant proposals for start up funding, and a proposal for an ecological cable channel written by Ryan which is an early iteration of his work on what he later called eco-channel design.
  Series is arranged alphabetically by organization name. Additional Raindance Corporation is filed in series 7, Printed Materials. Additional material related to Earthscore and other environmental organizations is found in series 3, Writings, and series 5, Project files.
  - Earth Environmental Group, circa 1975-1992 (Box 10, Folder 36-37)
  - Earthscore Foundation (Box 10)
    - Bank Records, 1974-1976; 1984 (Box 10, Folder 38-39)
    - By-Laws, circa 1974; 1976 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence, circa 1974-1982 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - Environmental Education Programs, circa 1984-1996 (Box 10, Folder 42)
      See also series 6, Teaching Files
    - Grant Proposals, circa 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 43-44)
    - Grant Proposals, circa 1983-1986 (Box 10, Folder 45-46)
    - Insurance, 1975-1977 (Box 10, Folder 47)
    - Notebook, circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 48)
    - Poster and Clipping, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 49)
      Oversized poster moved to OV 21.
    - Receipts, 1974-1976 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Tax Records, 1975-1985 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Writings, circa 1973-1992 (Box 11, Folder 3-5)
  - Environment '89 - Environment '92, 1989-1991 (Box 11, Folder 6-7)
  - Frisco Bay Mussel Group, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Gaia Institute (Box 11)
    - Correspondence and Writings, 1985-1987 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Formalizing Statement, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Gaia Curriculum Notes, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Notes, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 12-14)
    - Printed Material, circ 1985-1994 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      Oversized material in Box 20.
    - Professionals for the Earth Proposal, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Hudson Valley Meetings, 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Multimedia Access and Study Center (Kingston, NY), 1995 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Raindance Corporation (Box 11)
    See also series 7, Printed Materials.
    - Flyers and Catalogs, 1970-1991 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Photographs (contact sheet), circa 1970 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - "Supermarket" Essay, circa 1983 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - "Techniques" Interview with Paul Ryan, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Responsive Environments Corporation, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Space Videoarts, 1971-1973 (Box 11, Folder 24-25)
  - Oversized Gaia Institute Printed Material from Box 11, folder 15 (Box 20)
  - Oversized Earthscore Poster from Box 10, folder 49 (Box OV 21)
- Project Files, 1968-2008; Series 5; 6.5 Linear feet Boxes 11-17, 20, OV 21-22, 24, RD 26
  5.1: Environmental Projects
  5.2: Threeing Projects
  5.3: Other Projects
  Documentation is filed alphabetically under a project title where one exists. Projects for which only a proposal or outline exists are filed under the heading of proposals. Many of the projects and proposals represented in this series are related to one another and contain related documentation. Cross-references are supplied in the container listing to point researchers to related documentation.
  See also series 6, Teaching Files, for documentation of educational programs developed as an outgrowth of the Earthscore Notational System; series 4, Organizational Records, for records relating to organizations that supported Ryan's video work; and series 3, Writings, for related theoretical writings closely related to the projects in this series.
  Series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  This series includes documentation of projects Ryan carried out or participated in, including video productions, performances, conferences, art projects, and publications.
  Many of the projects documented in this series reflect Ryan's explorations of the use of video to monitor and interpret two seemingly different subjects, environmental change and human behavior in relationships, explored through a routine invented by Ryan called triadic behavior, or threeing. Other projects document early explorations of the use of video, mainly "Video Wake for my Father," a performance for video that saw many iterations, including a private performance, a public performance, an edited video program, and a published script.
  The series includes 47 videocassettes (U-Matic) out of the hundreds of video recordings created by Ryan. A printout of the database Ryan kept of his video recordings is available in series 5.3: Other Projects, under the heading "Video Preservation." Tape numbers listed in the container list for this series refer to numbers assigned in that database and on the tapes themselves.
  See detailed descriptions below for more information about the content of the series.
  - Environmental Projects, 5.1
    Note that the "Nature in New York City" videocassettes are arranged chronologically, which resulted in tape numbers listed being slightly out of sequence. The publication Talking Wood is found in series 7, Printed Materials.
    Series includes documentation from Ryan's environmentally-focused projects including "Nature in New York City," "New York City Eco-channel for a Sustainable Tomorrow (NEST)," the publication Talking Wood, the video project Tapping on Water, other unidentified projects involving the Earthscore Notational System, and many proposals for similar projects.
    Video recordings found in this series for "Nature in New York City," all U-matic videocassettes, include nine camera original videocassettes documenting the Bronx River waterfall, one videocassette documenting views of NYC shot from the World Trade Center, and one videocassette containing an early edited version of the piece. Notebooks for this project contain shotlists for video shot at Staten Island Clay Pit Ponds State Park, the Bronx River waterfall, the World Trade Center tapes, and saplings at Inwood Hill Park in Manhattan.
    Although most of the other environmental projects documented in this series involved the use of video, apart from "Nature in New York City," their documentation does not include video recordings. Records for NEST include correspondence, notes, a petition, and other records documenting an advocacy movement to dedicate a cable access channel to the environment. Records for Talking Wood include notes and photographs used in the publication. Tapping on Water is documented with a proposal, an artist statement, and a shotlist.
    - Nature in New York City (Box 11)
      - Video Recordings (Box 11)
        See box 17, folder 9 for a list of Ryan's video tapes from this and other projects.
        - Bronx Falls Unedited Footage, 1988 May 28 - June 10; 4 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes numbered W46, W48, W51, W49 20 minute tapes (Box 11, Folder 25-26)
        - Bronx Falls Unedited Footage, 1988 May 28 - June 10; 4 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tapes numbered W54, W53, W50, W47 20 minute tapes (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
        - Bronx Falls Unedited Footage, 1988 June 10; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tape numbered W52 20 minute tape (Box 12, Folder 3, Item 1)
        - World Trade Center Unedited Footage, 1988 June 2; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tape numbered W60 20 minute tape (Box 12, Folder 3, Item 2)
        - Edited Dub Master, 1988; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) Tape numbered W64 30 minute tape (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Notebooks (Box 12)
        - "Bronx Waterfall" Shotlists, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 5)
        - "Clay Pits," "Bronx Falls," "World Trade Center" Shotlists, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 6)
        - "Saplings" Shotlists, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 7)
        - Outline for Final Edit, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - New York City Eco-Channel for a Sustainable Tomorrow (NEST) (Box 12)
      - Contacts, circa 1990 (Box 12, Folder 9)